Guide to the William H. Claypoole Papers, 1941-19179 AIS.1982.16
ULS Archives & Special Collections
William H. Claypoole Papers
1941-1979
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Claypoole, William H.
AIS.1982.16
1.25 Linear Feet (3 boxes)
The Papers of William H. Claypoole consist of personal and political correspondence, scrapbooks, minutes, reports, speeches, and photographs, relating to Claypoole's campaigns, political service, and work with various charitable and civic organizations. Claypoole served as the Armstrong County Commissioner and as a Pennsylvania State Representative.
Biography
William H. Claypoole was born in West Franklin, Pennsylvania on March 30, 1907. In 1932 he was appointed by the Armstrong County Commissioners as Farm Manager of the county-owned farm in Kittanning. In August of the following year, 1933, he was appointed superintendent of the County Home and Farm.
In 1943 Claypoole successfully ran for Armstrong County Commissioner as served six four-year terms. He was elected President of the State Association of County Commissioners in 1958. During his tenure he was appointed by Governor John Fine to a board of seven to formulate property assessment to equalize the tax on property. Claypoole was also appointed to the Traffic Safety Committee by President Dwight D. Eisenhower. During his 23 years as County Commissioner, Claypoole was noted for the commissioners operating on a pay-as-you-go basis with no indebtedness. Also, in 1951-1952 the Board of Commissioners remodeled and enlarged the County Court House. It was recorded in the United States Congressional Records as the only Court House built and paid for upon completion. In 1966 Claypoole was elected State Representative of the 61st District and served two terms. Claypoole spent a total of 39 years in county and state government.
Claypoole was also active in civic and charitable affairs, such as serving on the Board of Directors of the Sheltered Workshop of Armstrong County, Historical Museum Society, Salvation Army, Cancer Society, County Animal Shelter, and the Heart Fund.
Claypoole was married to Ethel Heihnan in 1928 and they had one son, William R. Claypoole. After his retirement in 1971, Claypoole worked as a real estate appraiser for the Merchants National Bank. William H. Claypoole died February 25, 1981.
Scope and Content Notes
The Papers of William H. Claypoole consist of personal and political correspondence, scrapbooks, minutes, reports, speeches, and photographs, relating to Claypoole's campaigns, political service, and work with various charitable and civic organizations. The correspondence series includes proposals, occupation assessment, Armstrong County programs and institutions, complaints, and letters of recommendation, as well as a few items of personal correspondence with relatives who served in World War II. Additional correspondence, speeches, minutes, reports, printed material, and photographs can be found in the "Subject Files" series.
Claypoole's campaigns for election are well represented with correspondence, advertisements, announcements, speeches, records of contribution, and two scrapbooks for the years 1959 and 1966.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Informaiton
The collection was a gift of William R. Claypoole on August 9, 1982.
Previous Citation
William H. Claypoole Papers, 1941-1975, AIS.1982.16, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Claypoole, William H., 1907-1981, Papers, 1941-1979, AIS 82:16, Archives of Industrial Society, University Library System, University of Pittsburgh
Pennsylvania -- Politics and government -- 1951-; Personal papers; Politics; Associations; Armstrong County (Pa.) -- Politics and government; County government -- Pennsylvania; Elections -- Pennsylvania; Legislators -- Pennsylvania; Pennsylvania -- Politics and government -- 1865-1950; County officials and employees -- Pennsylvania; Charitable uses, trusts, and foundations -- Pennsylvania; Pennsylvania. General Assembly. House of Representatives; Armstrong County (Pa.). Board of County Commissioners; Claypoole, William H.
- Claypoole Family, 1941-1965; I.
  - Claypoole genealogy (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - William H. Claypoole autobiography (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Claypoole coat of arms (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1941-1965 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Newspaper clipping (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1942-1979; II.
  - General correspondence, 1942-1979 (Box 1, Folder 6-10)
  - Congratulatory letters, 1957-1971 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Speeches, undated; III.
  - Speeches, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Subject Files, 1941-1975; IV.
  - Armstrong County Court House Dedication, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 13-14)
  - Armstrong County Home and Farm, 1952-1975 (Box 1, Folder 15-23)
  - Armstrong County Industrial Development Council, 1966-1971 (Box 1, Folder 24-26)
  - Armstrong County Planning Commission, 1967-1971 (Box 2, Folder 27-28)
  - Armstrong County Prison, 1952, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Armstrong County -- Animal Shelter, n.d., 1971-1975 (Box 2, Folder 30-33)
  - Armstrong County -- Cancer Society, n.d., 1969-1970 (Box 2, Folder 34-35)
  - Armstrong County -- child welfare, 1952, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Armstrong County -- civil defense, 1960, 1964, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Armstrong County -- Civil Service employment, n.d., 1963 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Armstrong County -- conservation (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Armstrong County -- highways, 1955, 1957, 1967-1971 (Box 2, Folder 40-41)
  - Armstrong County -- history (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Armstrong County -- payroll, 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Armstrong County -- Progressive Workshop, 1975-1979 (Box 2, Folder 44-56)
  - Armstrong County -- Republican Committee, 1962, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Armstrong County -- Salvation Army, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Armstrong County -- Sheltered Workshop, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Armstrong County -- tax assessment, n.d., 1954, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Armstrong and Indiana Counties -- Mental Health and Retardation Program, 1967, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 61)
  - Boy Scouts and Girl Scouts (Box 3, Folder 62)
  - Campaign materials, 1943-1978 (Box 3, Folder 63-74)
  - County Commissioners (Box 3, Folder 75)
  - County government (Box 3, Folder 76)
  - Pennsylvania -- local health bill (Box 3, Folder 77)
  - Republican State Committee, 1956-1974 (Box 3, Folder 78)
  - Photographs and drawing (Box 3, Folder 79)